Hello, I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today RevenueCat CEO Jacob Idy.
Our guest today is Eric Crowley, a tech
investment banker with GP Bullhound,
where he provides transaction advice and
capital to top companies in the consumer
subscription software space. On the
podcast, we talk with Eric about the
rebound of consumer subscription
valuations and investor interest, how to
generate net revenue retention in
consumer, and why you should pinpoint
where your app sits on Maslow's
hierarchy of needs.
Hey Eric, thanks so much for joining us
on the podcast today. Thanks guys.
Always great to be here. Really
appreciate you having me back. Fifth
time on the podcast.
You're um most seasoned guest. It is
quite an honor. This is probably one of
the things I look forward to every year
to do. Is this why you do the report
now? You're like, if I don't do the
report, I'm not going to get on Sub Club
and that would just ruin my year. You
guys are so popular these days, I have
to keep my game up in order to get on
rocket. Got to keep up. And Jacob, nice
to be talking to you today as well. I'm
here. I'm good. I'm under prepared,
which is great cuz like uh Eric is over
prepared, so
But it's good. I'm always excited to
I don't know. We live We live the macro
at RevenueCat, right? Like dealing with
customers every day, but like it's nice
to get a chance to zoom out and look at
the industry uh a little bit more
broadly and make sure it's still here
and still growing. So
Yeah, and that's actually exactly where
I wanted to start is that uh we produce
the subscription apps report every year
now. Done the second, already planning
the third for 2025. This is your fifth
or fourth CSS report? And I feel like
your report in the fall is always this
nice kind of state of the industry. You
take a much broader look at the industry
than we do in our report and so it's
kind of a nice balance and yeah, reading
through a draft of your report this
week, I found a lot of really
interesting stuff that I, you know,
hadn't been thinking as deeply about.
But I did want to kick it off just kind
of talking, what is the state of the
subscription app industry? How are
things going from your point of view on
financing and M&A and all those kind of
things? Yeah, so well, thanks for having
us, guys. I think, you know, for the
people that haven't seen our report
before, we were an investment bank and
venture capital funds. So, we come at
the CSS industry as kind of like from a
transactional industry. We're not
builders like a lot of your listeners
are, but we are, you know, advisors or
investors into businesses in the
consumer subscription or as we call it
CSS
industry. So, our report kind of comes
at it from that angle, which is, you
know, how do you make how do you invest
or buy or sell companies in this space?
I mean, you guys know this from seeing
the data at the micro level, right? The
industry went through a huge boom in
2021. Tons of capital came flying in,
which meant tons of capital got spent on
marketing and growth and new ideas.
And then some of that
capital got put to waste, unfortunately.
So, like '22, '23 was a rough year for a
lot of these companies. Like they over
hired, their marketing returns went
down, they weren't able to scale nearly
as fast as they're hoping. And so, you
saw a lot of pain kind of happen in '22
and '23 with some companies going out of
business, a lot scaling down, switching
models, pivoting to B2B, e-commerce for
subscription.
But what I can tell you now in 2024 is
is things have probably never been
better. A lot of companies took their
medicine. A lot of really great founders
and builders kept their head down and
they kept doing exactly what their
mission was, which is serving their
customers.
And we are seeing better opportunities
and better companies now than we even
have in 2021. So, companies are growing
quickly, they're growing profitably,
they have retention rates that are just
fantastic. And so, you know, from a as a
M&A advisor, right? We generally see
well, we see our companies coming to
market when they're when they're ready
to do something, they'll give us a call.
And so, we've got this window, you know,
usually 6 to 9 months before a
transaction happens.
With hey, we know what great businesses
are to market. So, it's we've probably
never been busier, which is obviously
exciting for me, but hopefully it's
exciting for the industry over the next,
you know, 6 to 12 months. As you share
in the report, that's not only the case
in these private conversations that
you're having with apps looking to sell
or raise or whatever, but we see that in
the public valuations as well. Like
Duolingo is trading, I think in an
all-time, well, not an all-time revenue
multiple high compared to the 2021
bubble, but it's certainly rebounded
quite a bit since the drop. Yeah, I
think you see that across the board with
with some exceptions, right? There are
some businesses that had a huge COVID
booms, like some of the dating services
that just weren't able to keep that
level of growth up. They've said, "Hey,
we we probably over hired, over spent.
We're focusing on profitability, which
means, you know, their growth slowed and
their revenue multiples come down, but
they're still fantastic businesses
trading at good revenue multiples and
great EBITDA multiples.
So, I think that's you're just seeing
that shift, but that's also happening
across B2B software, it's happening
across technology where you know, if
you're not one of the Magnificent Seven,
you are evaluated on your financial
performance. And so, revenue, growth,
and EBITDA margins are becoming like how
the market evaluates SaaS business just
as they evaluate B2B SaaS businesses.
Yeah, in your report you mentioned this
idea of exceeding the rule of 40. I
didn't quite grok what you meant by that
in the report.
love to finally learn the rule 40 cuz
I've pretended to know it on occasion,
but It's bantered around a ton in the
investment universe. And it's almost
starting to be debunked, but for
listeners that haven't spent time on
this and and hopefully they have it.
They're building code. Rule of 40 is an
investment term. So, you take your
year-over-year growth rate, let's just
say your year-over-year growth rate is
30%. And then if you have an EBITDA
margin or cash flow margin of 10%, so
your the dollars of your cash flow you
have divided by your revenue, right?
That's And you add those two together,
you take 30% plus 10%, that's 40. At
least 40, right? The higher the better.
Yeah, the goal is the goal is higher,
right? And you can grow 60% and lose 10%
on EBITDA margin, so you have rule of
50. That still means you're doing well.
And so, in the public markets, I think
there's a slide in the report for people
to see, there's a really high
correlation on what multiple you trade
on, a revenue multiple, with what your
rule of 40 score is.
And that's been really intriguing, but
there's even another data point that'll
be in the report, which is the rule of
X.
Which effectively is Once you guys
understand rule 40, which we just did a
a quick intro on, now there's a rule X,
which effectively
there's a higher correlation with
companies that are growing faster. So,
if you take the math and say, instead of
just doing one revenue growth rate plus
the EBITDA margin, now if you do the
revenue growth rate times two
and add it to the EBITDA margin, so
you're kind of over weighting, you're
having over weighting the revenue growth
rate, that's actually even a higher
correlation. Correlates to about 60-70%
of the stock price versus, you know, the
other one was close the rule of 40 is
closer to about 56. And so, basically
that's just a, you know, a heuristic. Is
that something you guys came up with?
We definitely didn't come up with it.
That's I think one of the investment
funds, Bessemer, I think started it.
Bessemer did rule of X, which is pretty
cool. Just like uh they're just coming
up with like a a better model to to
match like trading values with like
growth rate and profitability. It's just
rules of thumb. Yeah, cuz the thing is
40, somebody just said like at some
point 40 is good, above that is good,
and below that is bad. Well, first of
all, it's uh mathematically heinous to
add your growth rate to your EBITDA
margin. They are both percentages, but
they are apples and oranges, right? Like
it's a weird thing, but it does happen
to kind of give you some information.
And like with the number 40, at least
and and maybe if I say this wrong, Eric,
correct me, but essentially like if
you're growing more than 40% a year,
it's okay if you're not profitable,
because you're growing 40% a year.
That's fine. Like you can burn some
amount, you know, for every point you're
over 40% growth rate, if you're losing
that percent on your margins, cash flow
margins, that's it's
But if you're below that, if you're
sub-40, probably you should be cash
flowing or at least like, you know, be
profitable. But, again, that 40 number
was some number some investment person
put on the board at some point. But,
it's notionally correct and interesting.
But, it's also telling if you're if
you're growing at 60 and losing 40, then
you're not hitting the rule of 42. So,
it's like you can't also just be
lighting cash on fire like it was 2021.
For RevenueCat, like we've gone above
and below for different reasons. Like,
we've had years where our growth rate is
really high, but our burn was really
high and we actually were below the
line. And then we've had years where our
growth rate stayed high, but we actually
got a little more fit fiscally. Still
losing money, but like in a more
responsible way. I don't know. This is
This is a thing that probably doesn't
concern me concern any SaaS company
under 5 or 10 million in revenue. I
don't think you should be looking at
this. But, when you're at the growth and
scale stages, it can be a helpful like
way to look at your business. It's a
rule of thumb. It's like walking 10,000
steps a day. Yeah, I mean, if you're not
looking to exit, focus on building your
business, right? Build the right thing
to your customers.
The these heuristics, these rules of
thumb, like they'll work themselves out.
And then to your point, right? Like,
it's a data point in a moment of time,
right? A company's not a data point.
It's it's a linear progression. Step
one, step two, step three, step four.
So, there may be years where like, yeah,
I'm going to spend a crap load of money
because there's this huge opportunity.
Yeah, and often that's when you need to,
right? Like, if the top of that number,
your growth rate starts to flag, you
might need to burn a lot more money to
like change the product or like figure
out a new growth thing. No, and some of
it is just investors like simple
analogies to help them narrow down
investment opportunities. And this is
one they use. So, yeah, so we report on
it. Yeah, super handy for folks in the
audience. So, I I I think we'll probably
have folks doing tens of millions of
dollars a year listening to this podcast
thinking about when the right exit
opportunity is and what kind of
multiples. So, yeah, a great rule to to
kind of
optimize toward if you are looking for
some kind of exit or funding or
otherwise in the short term. Yeah, you
should at least know what your metric
is. That's the best way to think about
it. It seems like M&A has also been hot
this year. A lot of CSS businesses on
the move. Yeah, it's been it's been
good. I mean, I think it's still early
days. There's a lot more coming. I think
we've been working on a few. You know,
there's a bunch of other ones like the 7
Max just bought Buddy Fit in Italy,
which is fitness.
Right? If you think about like fitness
apps still doing deals, that's pretty
exciting. You know, Outside just bought
MapMyFitness, which is uh from Under
Armour, which is a cool deal. That was
actually a founder buying back his own
company.
You know, there's there's been a bunch
of other cool stuff that's happening,
and I think we expect a lot more to
come. Like Bending Spoons has been busy.
Francisco Partners bought The Weather
Company, which is pretty cool. We helped
Team Snap buy Mojo. You know, that
business in the youth sports space,
which is we're really excited about
that. And then, you know, there's been
some financings that have been really
exciting. We were fortunate enough to
work with Flo Health. You guys know the
female health business. We just an
absolute phenomenal business. We helped
them raise a a really nice round from
General Atlantic. So, it's been been
really exciting. I know you can't go
super deep on Flo, but I did want to go
a little deeper. You talk about it some
in the in the report, but what is the
investment thesis? I mean, you know,
what was announced publicly is that, you
know, they raised 200 million at an over
billion-dollar valuation. And then in
the report you even share that they went
out looking for 100 million and ended up
in a very competitive situation where
they raised it to 200. So, what you can
share publicly, I'd love to hear a
little more uh color on on how that
happened and what the investment thesis
was behind such a high valuation and
then the competition to get in on it.
Yeah, so so Flo's been around for a long
time. Founded by Dmitry, you know, years
and years ago. And I've known him for,
you know, since 2019 since I started in
the industry. So, Flo was a female
health-focused business. It has a
freemium model. So, I think we've
disclosed this, but there's, you know,
north of 60, 60 million MAUs, and then,
you know, a fraction of that are
actually paid subscribers. And so, Flo
does a great job of providing females,
and now their partners, with information
around reproductive cycles, menstrual
health, and now they're moving into
perimenopause and menopause, which is
just really, really exciting. And so,
the thing like about this space, and
you'll talk about this when we get to
consumer ship, like other consumer
subscription areas, is it's super
crowded.
There's tons of that you can use Aura,
you could Apple Health. There's a And
those are big names, right, that
everyone knows. And then there's tons of
other female health-focused or period
tracking apps. What we really like about
Flo is that they will work with with
females early on, when they're kind of
like this the very beginning of their
health journey, you know, 15, 16, 17,
right, and they'll provide a free
product. And they kind of create this
data layer between when they're 18 all
the way till they're when they're 35,
40, 50, moving into perimenopause. And
then what you do is you can provide free
services to that individual as much as
they need. And then when they do need to
move into a paid program, right, there's
modules, effectively, that you can
subscribe to. You get all the services
of Flo Premium, but you can only maybe
only use one or two, or maybe use all of
them. But the cool thing is they're just
there when you need them.
And so then, what I think the thesis
from from GA was is you can just
continue to stitch and add new offerings
to the Flo to the Flo data layer, and
then that just increases the surface
area for where their, you know, 60
million MAUs will find a reason to
subscribe, and even if you capture one,
two, three percent of those with each
new module, that's hundreds of millions
in revenue.
And so, we were really excited about it.
I think the thesis was borne out. A lot
of investors saw that potential. You
know, we do think this is probably a
public company at some point. We're
really excited about that. And it's just
going to be another great CSS business
that's in the public market. So, yeah,
happy to answer any questions, but I
obviously have to keep most of
confidential. Yeah, yeah. I mean, I'll
do some analysis. 60 million, there's a
lot of people, there's billions of
potential users on the planet, so that's
a very good uh thesis. And then, I think
we've seen this play out multiple times
that like data generates retention,
right? Or like, the more somebody
invests in an app, and the more time
like horizontally it has with you, like
the higher your retention is going to
be. And that's something I always It's
not a debate we have so much anymore,
but I used to get a lot of people asking
me like, "Oh, should I make this a
subscription app? And like, how do I
like structure an app that's like worth
adding a subscription to?" And I think I
always counseled, and I still believe
this, that like
something that in gets better over time
will have naturally Well, one, it'll
justify a subscription because it's
something people use for years and
years. But then also, like the value
goes up. It compounds, you know, over
time. And so, yeah, I think this is a
very natural large human need, large
TAM. You know, it's a competitive space,
so it's interesting that there's there
would be one to emerge. I mean, that
does seem to be kind of how markets
develop over time is like once somebody
has kind of figured out the optimal
combination of current available
technologies, there will be like a small
oligopoly. So, that doesn't surprise me.
But yeah, it's interesting to think like
there's probably other categories that
haven't developed as much as Flow. And I
think it still speaks to the maturation.
60 million, that's like nobody. You know
what I mean? I don't know what the total
number of customers cuz there's some
slices on that from 8 billion people
down, but like but like obviously, we've
barely began Yeah, you're you're hitting
on the concept that we call category
killers, Jacob. And we talked about it a
little bit in the last report. We're in
consumer, right? Consumers flock to best
of breed, and they learn and decide what
best of breed is because other consumers
tell them. Word of mouth is such a such
a dominating channel, right?
you know, Flow is really special. I
think Demetrius talked about this, where
they get over 50% of their users are
organic.
All right, they've got great App Store
rankings, right? People, you know, moms
now are telling their daughters,
friends, girls in school tell each other
about it, right? So, it's it's really a
powerful flywheel. And so, we kind of
saw this in new sports, like where we
saw, you know, we think there'll be two,
maybe three winners in new sports. We
think Team Snap's one of those. We have
a couple predictions around financial
services, AI news.
Big one in family health or family
management. We call it the chief
household officer. We think there's
going to be a unicorn there, too. And I
think that's what RCS is practice is
oriented around, which is helping find
those unicorns early on, helping them
get to like the next level, and then
hopefully seeing them go public. But we
think there's a lot more to come. So, we
think Close Up are great examples of
what will be a lot of future public
companies. Well, things you mentioned in
there about Flow, and then also have a
whole slide in the report about is
finding ways to generate net revenue
retention in consumer subscription. And
those two acronyms don't usually go
together, CSS and NRR. At least positive
NRR. Yeah, exactly.
be positive or negative, so. But yeah, I
I'd love for you to walk us through your
thinking, and you kind of already talked
a little bit about it with Flow, and
kind of expanding the product. But what
are some of the other ways that consumer
subscription businesses can start
thinking about NRR being a possibility,
instead of just always being a kind of
net negative with all the churn going
on? Yeah, so the biggest So, when we
started the CSS practice, the biggest
thing we had to overcome was people were
like, well, this isn't B2B SaaS. The big
thing that people love about B2B SaaS is
once you land a customer,
hypothetically, you could sell them more
seats over time.
All right, so that, you know, you start
with 10 seats, then you go to 20 seats,
then you go to 30 seats. So, like, you
know, if Salesforce sells a customer,
right, they can gradually grow with that
customer. And that's really exciting,
right? Cuz the cost of landing them
takes one time, and then you add more
revenue, and it's it becomes an
extremely profitable business model.
The issue people
think they see with consumer is that you
sell a consumer once, and then that
price is capped, right? You sell them
for $29.99, for example, for a year.
That's all the money you'll make from
that individual, best case. And then
there's such high churn that you you get
this positive net revenue retention.
And you know, the answer is that's not
true. It's not
always not common, but in the best of
breed CSS businesses, the way to think
about this is every consumer
subscription business has churn. And
most of them are high churn. The
question is when does that churn
stabilize? Like when do you find what we
call within our in the in our GVB CSS
report, like the locals versus the
tourists.
So to use an example, if you start with
100 users
and you churn 50 in your first year all
in annual subscriptions, you're down to
50 users. Then the second year you keep
45 of those 50, right? So now you have
40%. But then the third year you keep
43. All right, and then the fourth year
you keep 42. So now all of a sudden that
parabola has just flatlined. And so like
effectively your dollar revenue
retention is equal. But then here's
where the NRR can start to play in is
CSS businesses have sure that you can do
price increases. So we have this in our
report which we kind of graph Amazon's
Prime subscription, Netflix's cost, and
Hulu's cost cuz those are all mostly
public. And they go up every 2 years,
right? And so all of a sudden now you're
seeing pricing expansion which is David
you kind of asked like how do you get
NRR? So now if you have a flat cohort
number of users, you're just adding
price increases, right? Which can
overcome Double-digit compounded
inflation will help drive the market to
being accepting of And that's the only
way you can get away with that, like for
sure. But then you see other ways to
monetize, right? Like Spotify, Duolingo,
they launched family plans. So they now
they acquired the mom and then the mom
brought in an app for the dad and the
the family. So now there's a family
plan. So you just got you had user
expansion with that same one customer.
You can upsell new features. Right? Like
Quicken, OnX, they've OnX launched like
global maps, right? Versus just your
state maps so you can upgrade to a
higher tier. Quicken's adding like a
state planning tools, really cool. So if
you already are on their financial
management software, now you can do
wills and trusts and have like a locker
to store like important documents.
That's an easy upgrade for users. And so
we're seeing some really cool ways that
that CSS businesses are generating net
revenue retention, but it does require
you to really dig deep in the data and
understand, you know, how do these
businesses work? How do What do
consumers value? And then, once again,
like back to the point, how do you bring
more value to that same subscription,
which may justify a price increase or
just keep them subscribing. Like, both
of those things really could be useful.
It's really not a lever worth pulling
until you've in CSS, until you've
compounded a handful of years and like
you've got you've got a base of of
sturdy long-term subscribers that you
can when risk to churn them a little
bit. But then also just to have a body
of like long-termers that you can
actually either offer something to or
even a price increase. I don't think the
price increase thing is
Yeah, I think Netflix and and Disney did
a good job of paving the expectation for
that from a consumer perspective.
Simultaneously with the price increases
in pretty much everything everywhere. I
used to be very against this because
like I thought I don't know. I just
thought it was like I'm not worth doing,
not worth the negative press, which
again I think for most scaling early
stage it's not, but when you're late
stage, when you've got like a very
mature subscriber base and you're
starting, you know,
that 40 doesn't add up itself, you know
what I mean? You got to like you got to
find each point. Like I think there's I
think there's a case to be made that
it's it's it's an okay thing to do. You
have to justify it to users, right? You
can't sneak it in. You send an email,
you say, "Hey guys, we're going up to
$29.99 to $35.99 and here's why. Here's
all the benefits you're getting for that
extra six bucks." Once again, like if if
they're truly your users, right? If
they're truly people that have been
subscribing for two to three years and
they're like, "Yeah, I use this product
every month or I use it once a year for
my big camping trip." or hey, I I log
into this every day, they're not
churning. Just send them a link to the
uh
inflation report for the last You can AB
test this stuff. Like a lot of companies
AB test, right? They try a little bit,
see what the retention is, but generally
like what I found with most of my
clients is that if you're best of breed
and you're producing a good quality
service, people are going to get it.
Yeah, you have margin you have
uncaptured margin basically, right? Like
that's what you're leaving on the table.
It's not just trying to get a fair
price. And I don't know. I think there's
some argument that you can have like an
asymmetric power there. Like if you've
like captured people's data and like you
know, I don't know. I think it's there's
some there's some amount of balance you
want to do there, but you know, I don't
know. Ideally, we're finding the
the optimums of pricing. Yeah, I don't I
don't with value capture thing, I don't
ever
buy into that cuz there's just a lot of
options for consumers. So like if you
offend someone, right? If you personally
offend them with however you message it
or like, "Hey, you can't earn cuz I've
got your information."
They'll be a little
pissed, right? And so like when you're
creating this this desire to get back at
you.
All right? So like you don't want that.
You just want like, "Hey guys, we're
doing the best for you, but this is
what's best for us. So let's just meet
in the middle." And I think consumers
are totally fine with that.
I think founders typically, depending on
how close you are to the product, it's
probably once probably once you're
talking about rule 40, this is no longer
a concern. But when it's like an auteur
person who remembers not charging
anything for their product, it can be
very very uncomfortable cuz some
somebody will be pissed. And like you
just have to be okay with that. For
sure. It's going to happen. If you're
not okay with one person being pissed,
you probably shouldn't have started a
company or built an app cuz like it's
just comes with the territory a little
bit.
We haven't talked about yet. I don't
think you explicitly mentioned in the
report, but a lot of CSS businesses are
also cracking the code on on one-time
purchases as well of like add-ons.
Duolingo being a great example of that.
I don't think in their numbers they're
showing cuz they they do still have
pretty high churns. I don't think
they're anywhere close to NRR positive
yet, but they're driving that direction
with the like buying the I forget what
all the little things are like, you
know, streak recovery and things like
that. It's definitely something apps can
and should be exploring. For sure. I
mean, Tinder's been doing this for
years, right? You could buy baskets of
super likes, right? They're not a
subscription, but it enhances your
ability to use the product. All right, I
think we're I think we're going to see
more and more of that with CSS
especially as you can do more and more
targeted customization around offers,
around the products you're actually
selling with some of these AI tools.
There's you could do one-off maps, you
could do specific layers. I think you
see this in a lot of the prosumer tools.
All right, if you want to create your
own personal template or email template
or something like that. That's a That's
a one-time purchase. So, there's there's
a lot of cool stuff coming and I think I
think it's just going to get more
interesting. So, I think David, to your
point, stick to the subscription. That's
where the vast amount of money is but if
there is something you could offer your
users without taking your eye off the
ball on a subscription.
I think it's something to think through.
We've kind of been talking mostly about
the upside but there also are a lot of
threats in in the industry
one of which directly applies to Flow
and I'm actually going to have the we're
going to have the the founder Dimitri on
the podcast soon and so I've actually
already spoken to him so little preview
of that episode but he has some
interesting thoughts around when Apple
Health came into this their space, you
know, they introduced period tracking as
a default part of the OS. AllTrails is
facing that with iOS 18 adding hiking
maps right into the built-in map. So,
how do you think about the threat of
platform owners expanding into these
product spaces? Most of these services
rely on Apple and Google for some
some level of either customer
acquisition, some features, right? Using
the hardware that Apple and Google I'm
kind of focusing on those two but you
can expand this to Oura, you can expand
it to Whoop are generating, right? And
so, you're at risk there. And I think,
you know, Apple let's just kind of focus
on Apple, right? Because they generally
get most of the the slings and arrows
tossed at them. They're really valuable
participant in this ecosystem. You can't
knock that but I think they're starting
to get a little pressure because they
charge pretty high fees, right? The 30%
fee.
And then they also they have a history
of and this term Sherlocking which is
coming from a historical thing they've
done uh uh with another app called
Watson, where they'll kind of copy
features that are highly used in some of
their main apps and kind of just
continue to build the Apple service
ecosystem. And so, I mean, you guys
probably see this from their public
reports, like their hardware sales are
slowing. Our services sales are growing
like wildfire. And so, a lot of stuff
they're offering for free, like maps,
they'll put the the AllTrails or the
hiking maps into the map services just
to get more people to use maps, right?
Because they can start to sell more and
more ads off that. They're adding more
data into health, that helps them sell
watches. That's a value-add service for
them. So, if you're a founder and you're
building, I think one of the people
always talk about at Apple Demo Day is
Startup Death Day, right? You just never
know when Apple releases something that
is perfectly designed to what you were
trying to solve for. And so, yeah, it's
a competitive threat. There's no denying
there's no papering over it. But, the
silver lining is is like Apple is a big
juggernaut. They bring a lot of people
awareness to the category, right? So,
there's a certain thing they add to it,
people now become aware of that feature,
they'll look for best of breed. So, if
you're a top 20% app, this could be a
benefit for you, right? But, you have to
constantly keep innovating. You can't
just build an app, like, you know, to
use AllTrails as an example, they can't
just stop doing stuff and say, "Well,
we're good." Right? They always have to
be 10x better than whatever Apple's
offering is, right? More photos, more
reviews. Now, they're doing social
features, right? Apple doesn't do any of
that. You know, what happens is I think,
you know, if you've got to use Flow and
AllTrails as an example, like Apple may
clip off a couple of percentage of their
free users, but what they don't do is
they don't take the people that would
pay for AllTrails and Flow. Those people
do not just stay on Apple, right?
They're trying to look for a premium
experience, so they will go premium.
But, if you're you the negative side,
right? If you're an app that hasn't
innovated, you're kind of just a me too
app sitting at, you know, the bottom of
the ranks the rankings in the App Store,
that's hard. It's a hard as hell to be.
And so, investors are pretty smart about
that, so you You be really knowledgeable
and and our ability to overcome like
that challenge question, which is going
to come up. I like the way you frame it
in the report, too, that
there's broad and shallow, which is what
the platforms do. It's like they like
when they introduce period tracking in
Apple Watch, like they had to do it for
the masses. It's it's broad and shallow.
It's not a super deep feature. And then
Flow is like the exact opposite. And
then the way you frame it in the report
is verticalized and deep where they have
so many other features and layered upon
like to your point earlier, it's like
the things that people are going to pay
for in Flow are the things Apple is just
never going to add to this mass market
app. So the the best defense against
Sherlocking is building a real moat with
that depth and verticalized product
offering instead of doing that kind of
me-too
thing that puts you at huge risk. Has
there ever been any other app besides
Watson that was Sherlocked?
Actually Sherlocked, right? Yeah. Yeah,
I feel like it's something everybody
talks about all the time, but it like
never actually had like who was it
recently? 1Password, cuz they Apple like
upgraded all their password stuff. And
everyone was like, "Whoa, 1Password's
over." And I'm like
like we use 1Password business syncing,
all of that stuff, cross-platform? No,
never in a million years. Like they're
going to you know, well, one, I think
probably people are overtuned to the
Apple ecosystem talkers, you know, who
think like, "Oh, I'll just do everything
through Apple." I don't know. I just
don't think there's been actually that
many cases. Or nothing meaningful to
kind of to Eric's point. It's like the
me-toos, yeah, sure, maybe they got
dropped off, but like nothing we care
about.
I think maybe I would think twice if if
there was a great like OS level solution
already, I might think twice about
starting something new in there. But if
you're already in that space, and I
guess yeah, if you're not like just
nascent, like very beginning, if your
product has any sort of differentiation
whatsoever, like Apple and Google or
whoever, they're building it because
there's something there. Like they would
not care unless it was substantial. And
so, I'm a believer in most of the time
it's it's kind of a boon or at least
neutral the exception of like maybe a
few cases, but If you're best to breed.
So, think about it like from a
note-taking standpoint. Right? Notion's
probably going to survive any AI tools
that Apple integrates in the notes,
right? They'll probably survive. Or
there's a bunch of other note-taking
apps that may have a really rough time
capturing customers. So, Notion probably
fine, right? Then I don't know Notion,
you know, I don't have no impact
information. But, if you're someone else
and then an AI and Apple all of a sudden
integrates like some bunch of other
tools or kind of starts to look a little
more like Google Docs within their notes
platform, that could be a tough spot to
be. I'm using some of the transcription
services in Apple's voicemail. Pretty
good. Right? So, if you're using
something a separate product, could be a
problem. You can't stop filling in the
spaces cuz Apple exists. It's like what
people used to do in social networks.
Like, "Oh my god, Google's doing
something. Facebook's is dead." Well,
No, David, I'm trying to get there any
are there I'm trying I can't think of
one tool that I've like switched to the
OS level on. You know, the notes is a
good example though cuz as Apple added
more and more to notes, this was
probably 5 years ago, I stopped using a
third-party notes app. It's true. Yeah,
cuz they used to not have sync. Like
their sync is really good now and like
great app. Yeah, yeah. It's really is a
fantastic app. But, it's not like I
never used Evernote. I was using
actually perfectly validates Eric's
point is like I was using kind of a a
more bare-bones me too third-party notes
app that didn't didn't even have like
super sophisticated syncing, wasn't
super feature-rich. And so, moving to
Apple's notes just made a ton of sense
as they've added all these features.
But, I wasn't an Evernote kind of power
user.
Yeah, on the AI side though, too, it's
like the system level notes app will now
habituate users to some of those
features. And then Apple's not going to
update them but once a year if that,
right? And so, now everybody else is
building AI integrated has like a
warm-up app that everybody uses then
you're in class and you see somebody
next to you using something crazier and
you're like, "Oh, you don't use
whatever." And then it's like, "Well,
I'm going to switch to that, right?" So,
this stuff's so dynamic and so like hard
to fully characterize like consumer
behavior that I I I I I I I I I I I I I
I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I
I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I I No,
that's a fantastic point. Like Apple is
unlikely to integrate AI features into
the notes app at the level that would
kind of be meaningful for me, but now
that you bring that up, I would actually
I mean I have so many notes now going
back five or six years since I like
started using it more in depth that like
hard to find. It'd be hard to switch,
right? No, no, no, but I'm saying it's
like more incentive to switch with AI
companies really get aggressive with
better tooling and finding and rag
search and all that kind of stuff. Yeah.
Cuz with the AI piece I think
specifically we didn't put this in the
report, but if you think about it,
they're going to need access to data,
right? And so they will want specific
requests like access to your contacts,
access to your calendar tools. Apple's
going to be a little protective on that,
but which one are the consumers going to
trust to unleash an AI engine on their
own personal information? So, I think
there's there's a double-edged sword
there, too. Like I think the founders
and well the builders don't know
integrate AI tools so much faster than
Apple. Just factor of like probably 3x.
Two or three years ahead of Apple, but
if you want to trust someone with your
data source like your core data like
contacts or calendar, Apple might have a
slight advantage there. So, you really
have to connect with this premium
offering to get that consumer buy-in
which is like, "Hey, what are my friends
using? Do they love it? Cool." And I'll
then I'll use that app. I don't want to
go super deep cuz it's it's just been
talked about a ton, but because it is
being talked about a ton, I'd love to
just kind of get the read of the room on
like the DMA and all the regulatory
kind of overhang we have. It's over.
Terry resigned. It's going away, right?
I thought it just when he left, it's
over. No, that's not how Europe works.
Okay.
But how is that like being priced into
acquisitions? How is it being priced
into investments? How is the investment
community thinking about regulation both
positively and negatively? Yeah, I mean
so I mean DMA side and focus on it for
people that don't know what that is.
It's the Digital Markets Act. So it's
it's a it's a legislation instituted by
the EU and I think what it's designed to
do is kind of loosen the grip that some
of the large platforms specifically like
Apple, Google have on independent
developers.
And there's a couple areas, right? They
kind of restrict payments for one which
everyone's very focused on it. They also
restrict a lot of other stuff like how
you do marketing, all the discounts,
offerings, stuff like that,
customization. App review. App review,
yeah. So we're I just had a couple of
run-ins with app review in my side
project app.
Is David suddenly pro-DMA?
It's like
He's like I've never been more proud of
French French legislation than now. So
but I think like this is something like
the EU generally has been on the
forefront of privacy. They're with they
do generally sometimes first
occasionally felt there's already here
to the US. But it's pretty hot topic
right now. It's really hard to price.
Right? So everyone's kind of saying like
can I just assume Apple's 30% goes to 15
and the company gets 15% more
profitable? No, you can't. Can I tell
you for sure every one of my clients is
looking at some sort of a web
subscription offering? For sure. Right?
And those are getting better and better.
I think RevenueCat's working on some
stuff. There's a bunch of other names
that are that are thinking about how do
we offer a web subscription tool that it
provides the same features that the App
Store does which is user management,
taxes, payment, making sure that like
you're collecting taxes appropriately in
every jurisdiction.
With all but at a 5 to 7% commission
rate versus 30%. Right? And I think
there's there's going to be some big
changes once these products scale and
they get really, really good which the
App Store's had a 10-year lead on doing
something like that. I think consumers
are going to be comfortable to take a
10, 20% discount and sign in through the
web real quick and then come back to an
app. I think we're going to get trained
on that just like we got trained on how
we do subscriptions. But yeah, so I It's
hard to say what else will happen in the
next 4 years, but it's definitely a hot
topic. Yeah, I mean there's there's been
a lot of energy around the like web
funnel capture, and there's been some
new tech that's people are building
tools for this, but none of that's like
driven by the DMA. Like a lot of that
was allowed before. I will be interested
to see if any of these stores reach any
sort of like escape velocity. I just
think the size of the market is too
restrictive for it to reach any sort of
meaningful scale national
internationally.
And honestly, this is like we're
recording this the week after Thierry
Breton, I think it's his name, who was
the head of DMA resigned or was asked to
resign, which I do think I do think
marks kind of a potential I mean, who
knows? I don't know what the internal
politics of the commission are, but I
think like marks potentially a sea
change. I don't know if that means the
DMA will change or at least like maybe
enforcement will not become a thing
anymore, but he was pretty actively
harassing Apple the last last year on
specific details. Like you can imagine a
version of the DMA is out. Apple shipped
their version, and then the EC just shut
up, and then that was it. But like we've
gone through the last year where it's
been tick and tack and back and forth in
a big uncertain mess. Even if it just
goes to back to like, okay, the status
quo, I think that's good for I mean,
maybe it's not the outcome everybody
wanted, but I think that's good for the
industry in terms of like maybe we've
got some stability. But yeah, I'm just
I'm just hopeful maybe it'll be a little
less exciting in the next year.
That would be a dream for me. I think
people like predictability and
stability. It's true. I mean, it's it's
it's cliche potentially, but like hey,
like I you know, and if we want to build
anything with these platforms or these
changes or these openings, we need
stability, and we need like time to like
be like, okay, how do we actually
integrate this stuff? But yeah, I go
back to your prediction then just there
will be more people driving to the web.
I just think that's generally going to
be true. I think experiences that will
still stay in app. I'm still like a big
believer that the user experience delta
between what can be provided in a web
browser and what I think there was a
there was a decade there where we
thought the web browser would get
developed enough that it was going to
overtake, but the two biggest makers of
web browsers are Apple and Google. So,
they have a big incentive to make sure
the browser never gets too good, right?
So, I don't think we're going to see
that anytime soon. This trend though is
also kind of on Apple, right? And so,
there is tools in their tool shed to to
reverse that trend it. Like there are
ways that they can more strongly
incentivize in-app purchase. And and
like to your point earlier, Eric, like
the tools for doing these things aren't
fully mature. Like Stripe just bought
Lemon Squeezy. I saw a job posting for a
like manager of merchant of record. So,
it's like Stripe is looks like they're
building a Stripe-branded merchant of
record similar to what Paddle does, but
it's like they're just now doing that.
And so, like there's not And then even
Stripe today doesn't support all the
countries and all the payment methods
and all the things that the App Store
does. And so, there's potential here for
Apple to innovate. And that's what you
want in good regulation and good policy
is to force somebody like Apple to be
more competitive versus just collecting
the 30% and resting on their laurels.
So, I'm kind of curious to see what
happens in the next couple of years if
they kind of fight back a little. None
of this is DMA triggered though. Paddle
and like all this stuff was happening
already and Apple may or may not react
and actually that was what caused it,
right? But I'm sure somebody will be
like, "Well, then there was the DMA and
then Apple got better." And it's like,
"Well, no, I think they were going to do
that anyway, but okay."
Yeah, no, good point. But yeah, it's
still going to be interesting to see
what what happens. And I'm especially
curious to see what Apple does to kind
of shift that cuz there's definitely a
trend toward it. Like Eric was saying,
like there's a trend toward people
trying to capture more and more on the
web to avoid that 30%. So, like surely
Apple's has seen that and is uh trying
to figure out what to do and then surely
you know Google has the other half of
the oligopoly.
It will either follow suit or have their
own innovative approach to trying to win
some of that back.
In the report you talk a little bit
about IPOs and how CSS relationship to
IPOs. I think we're at a really
interesting time right now in the public
markets or lack thereof. I think there's
only been like four IPOs this year. So
I'm sure there's more but four that are
like on my radar. It's been extremely
probably one of the most intense
droughts in public and that's in the B2B
side even. So when you look at consumer
items I have to assume it's been
actually worse. So I'm curious like you
know on the less it seems like more
deals that are less than going public
more like private equity acquisitions
and stuff like this but how do you see
the
I guess the IPO market broadly and then
how it applies to this segment. Yeah I
mean I think you're dead on Jacob like
IPOs are down big from 2021 for sure
2022. I don't I don't think we're even
at 2018-2019 levels. So I think there's
a lot of investors hunger for cash but
there's a lot of private deals happening
like Stripe's a perfect example you
mentioned them earlier. They've done
tons of secondary deals. Right? So
instead of going public they're like
cool we'll just collect a check and be
able to pay out some of our investors.
Yeah and the only loser is retail right?
Yeah so like they just go public later
right? Like so that's that's the risk.
And like just to put it like a
quantifier on it they're at billions of
revenue right? Like they're at an insane
scale. And like there's a lot of
consumer businesses that went public
like an Allbirds you know that went
public during kind of
back the back time frame that went
public with SPACs.
It's super hard to be a small scale
public company but it doesn't have some
level of predictability. Right? Even
Bumble which is a household name right?
That's got billions of revenue their
stock's gotten pounded. Right?
Duolingo's done really well so it's
definitely a have and have nots. Do you
think there's a world where somebody
replicates Duolingo's success in the
public markets on consumer's side? I
think I might have worked with one
recently. Yeah.
Okay.
So, I definitely do. I think there's
great CSS businesses that are starting
to scale. You know, if you start to get
to 4 or 500 million in revenue, can
you're predictable like public markets
like that, right? They can see that
path, right? Hey, you're going public at
500 million, now you're closer to 750 on
a way to 750 and profitable on your own
destiny. People buy that.
It's easy numbers to say, but when when
you talk about like just like to get to
that scale is such an insane journey and
like just numbers. Like there how many
subscription apps
at least like purely I if you just look
at like just iOS apps, there's maybe 15
like even in that realm. I think there's
some pretty good ones out there. I mean,
you can kind of start going like down
the line, right? There's people have
everyone knows Strava, right? Couple
hundred million. You've got do You've
got Discord, right? All of a sudden,
that's a pretty big one. Right? Or a
kind of a hardware manufacturer with a
subscription offering, right? Where you
know, they're probably someone that
could go public and kind of compete with
a Garmin, right? With the health and
wellness, right? That's there's a play
there. I think there's more than you'd
think, right? There's a lot of
information I have that I probably can't
chat through. There's great companies
out there that are in serious scale that
just don't want to go public yet.
Is the constraint on the companies not
wanting to do it because of like the
blood in the streets? Like it's it's
gnarly out there or is it more on the
buy side there's just like public market
investors aren't really interested? It's
a little bit of both, right? Like if
you're a founder and you're like, "Man,
I'm still with Strava. I'm growing. I'm
growing. I've got a lot of things going
on. I'm focused on product. Do you want
to go deal with the public markets and
do quarterly projections?"
No. Oh, you weren't asking me. That was
a bad setup. Maybe something you'll get
at. Not that I'm at the scale, not that
anybody would think, but you got to, you
know. But so then then you look at the
public markets guys, right? And a lot of
those guys have taken a bloodbath. Yeah,
I don't know if I've ever met a founder
whose public market stock is higher than
their IPO price.
That just might be a unique
time in my life. There's a lot out
there. right? a lot out there.
Presumably went IPO in like 2002 or
something, I'm guessing.
If you IPO'd in '21, good chance you're
underwater. But hey, as we record this,
the Fed just dropped 50 basis points, so
money's free again, right?
Yeah, great. Great. I should IPO'd
yesterday. Damn it. There's secondary
available, right? Like the you know,
deal we've been seeing get done and
we've done. There's a lot of secondary,
so like there's money out there swapping
around that are not in the public
markets that are very happy to do
secondary deals. And so if that exists,
guys, that kind of solves the problem,
it relieves the pressure from the from
your employees, your your investors, and
then it also still gets money into your
company. Like that's an easy answer,
right? So like why go public until you
really need that net mark? I just really
want to deny private market investors
their fees, Eric. That's really what my
Just two and 20, I can't I can't suffer
it. E*TRADE's a lot more efficient, but
That's totally fair. Two and 20s are a
happy shock. I'm not going to I'm not
going to deny that. Yeah, well, I it's
an interesting time. We'll see. It's
going to be one of two. Like one, we're
just in like a pretty heavy market
depression on companies going public and
then we'll turn to a healthier, like
more accessible final destination for
companies. But I do worry about like the
broader macroeconomic impacts of the
fact that only high-net-worth
individuals and you know, the folks that
manage their money are the ones who are
able to invest in like small cap
companies because that's where the most
growth is, right? Which I think will
have like negative implications for, you
know, wealth inequality and things like
this. I mean, maybe it's not
substantial, but I think it is a loss. I
think the world we had in in some of the
2010s and you know, going back to even
like the the 2000s where, you know,
going public was just a thing you did
once you had some amount of scale and
some amount modicum of predictability is
is gone. But I think too, though,
probably as you were saying, it's it's a
very rare situation even find yourself
considering that. I think a lot more
founders, if you know, coming to an exit
is something that you're interested in.
I think there's much more There's much
easier paths than than aiming to public
with much less work, frankly. So. Well,
and that's what you covered in the
report. I mean, there's a whole slide on
other good outcomes for CSS businesses.
And I did want to actually talk through
some of those. So, other than striving
for AP IPO, what are some of the
outcomes you're seeing your clients look
toward as great outcomes for their
businesses? Yeah, I think we've covered
the why IPOs are positive negatives, but
I mean, the cool thing about CSS is
there's a lot of people that want to own
great CSS businesses. And so, you know,
we sold a business called NutriCheck to
a content company called Immediate
Media. And so, they were able to
effectively say, "Hey, we want we have
an ad-driven model with tons of MAUs,
people looking at our content. We need a
subscription offering for that, right?"
And so, that was a home run deal. So, it
was a subscription business selling to a
content business. And you put those two
together, and that just solved a lot of
CAC questions. You know, private equity
actively looking at the space, right?
So, they're actively looking at great
businesses that are cash flowing just
like they would, you know, a car wash
business. They like growth businesses
that have that have nice predictable
revenue streams. CSS is literally the
definition of that. And then, you know,
there's there's founder-owned
businesses. We're seeing lots of people
just be like, "Hey, I'm good to go." And
they'll sit there and they'll collect
their dividend, and it's it's a
phenomenal outcome for them. And that
that is not a bad thing. And then, one
area we're really excited about is these
CSS aggregators. We kind of talked about
this a while back, but there's a ton.
There's like 5 million businesses in the
App Store that are generating money,
right? That's a lot of companies. And
most are small. You know, there's very
few that are to Jacob's point are like
north of 500 million in revenue. That's
really rare. But there are a bunch that
are doing 5, 10, 15 million in revenue
profitably. I bet a lot are revenue CAC
customers.
And so, what we start to see are these
CSS aggregators. And there's a bunch
We'll name a bunch in our report. I
won't do it here. But they're buying
these companies up for multiples of
EBITDA. They're giving founders
liquidity. They're taking over the app.
Sometimes they bring the team. Sometimes
they don't. It kind of depends on the on
the buyer. And these are great sources
of liquidity for founders. And so, we're
seeing these guys really scale, they're
railing raising institutional capital.
And like we're kind of sitting there
like the Berkshire Hathaway of the App
Store. As they're going through, they're
buying these things on they're valued
fairly, but they're not getting revenue
multiples, right? These guys buy off
EBITDA multiples. So, if you're
generating EBITDA and you're saying,
"Hey, I'm just done. I want to go off
and do something else. I think I can get
20, 30 million in my pocket, or I can go
raise a VC round and then I have to sell
for 100 million."
That's a pretty good option as a founder
to think about. And so, we're seeing
that happen quite a bit right now. So,
like Bending Spoons, for example, bought
Evernote. Really good example. They
bought WeTransfer, as well.
There's And there's a bunch of these
coming in Europe, specifically, and then
a few here in the US. Is there a theory
of the case like why they're more common
in Europe than here? Might just be that
Bending Spoons is in Europe. Like that
could be part of it. Sure, Bending
Spoons is definitely in Europe. And
they're the ones doing the most of it,
it seems like.
They're They're great. Yeah, they're
really smart operators. But I think
there's a couple of things. One, there's
a little more affordable technical
talent over in Europe. Sure, if you if
you're not going to bring in
team, right? Someone's running the
business for you, right? Yeah, so just
like high profit margin businesses. Like
two businesses with equal every
everything else equal is going to have a
higher margin in in like a lower cost of
living place. Yeah. Right. If you can
still capture do the marketing, right,
correctly, still capture US consumers,
right? So, I think they're seeing We've
seen stuff like that really scale. Also,
some of the talent over there is just
phenomenal. And they really understand
marketing. They know the best of breed
practices, right? They're implementing
AI left and right. And so, they they've
been able to scale businesses that like
some of them that we haven't heard of
here in the the TechCrunch world, if you
will, that are used by hundreds of
millions of people around the globe.
They just don't happen to sit in Silicon
Valley or Austins, they don't get the
press. But they're big big businesses. I
think it's also worth pointing out that
like exits are only needed if you need
an exit.
Like I think it's good if you do want an
exit, then you need to know these
things, and you should plan accordingly.
And I think there are some choices you
can make strategically as a business
owner to like plan for that and to give
yourself optionality.
But I also say like if
you don't see yourself needing a lot of
liquidity in the short term and like
you're in it for the long haul, then
go back to the original algorithm Eric
will say and just focus on your
business, keep your head down and cuz
the market's going to look completely
like if you're not going to sell for 10
years or 15 years or 20 years, the
market's going to be completely in a
different shape and a lot of this advice
might be moot. The only thing that will
probably stand the test of time is good
businesses that build good products that
do it efficiently, right? Like that that
will always be true. Yeah, and that's
that's the last one we just said, keep
your cash cow. Like I know lots of
founders in San Francisco around the
globe that have like a nice business
kicking out three, four million of
EBITDA to them. They take some nice
dividends and they're happy. Like you
know, it's a great life.
All right, so you don't need the
TechCrunch article. You don't need to
call me, right, to sell your business
for $50 million. I'm a phenomenal
outcome situation. So I think that's
becoming more and more common to people
and then like we give that advice all
the time like hey, like we don't think
this is going to sell for $50 million.
So
sit there, hold on it, like buy a nice
second house, live a good life. All
right, the last thing I did want to talk
as we wrap up is you have this slide
called Maslow's hierarchy of
subscription. And I thought this was a
fun place, kind of an optimistic place
to kind of end the the episode here.
What do you mean by that and then where
do you see the opportunities? So I think
a lot of people are familiar with
Maslow's hierarchy of needs. And this is
a, you know, a psychology term
effectively where it just kind of
describes like how do consumers focus
their life and their goals, how they
orient their lives. And it's so starting
from the bottom up and I, you know,
there's no illustration here, but you
kind of focus on food, water, shelter
first, right? The basics just to stay
alive. And you go safety, right? Are you
kind of happy, healthy, right? Is your
family happy and healthy? But then it
starts to get a little more esoteric, a
little more like personal
self-fulfillment. You've got love and
belonging, like do you have someone
you're you're a partner, are you part of
a community that you really feel part
of? Then you have esteem, like do you
feel really good about who you are,
right? Like you personally are you happy
with your health, your looks, your
fitness? And then you have
self-actualization, which is I want to
be better than I am today, so I'm doing
something to improve myself, right? And
so
we talked about this last year that
that if you're building a great CSS
business
tying it to passion is a great way to
enhance retention, and passion ties to
identity.
Right? So if you think about this, if I
say, "Yeah, I'm a Strava user." Well,
what do you think What are these What
does that person think? Well, they're
probably an athlete. They probably care
about fitness. Right? So that's it's an
identity. If you're a Surfline user,
you're a surfer. Right? That's just who
you are, you know, it's it's who you
identify as. If you use Team Snap,
you're probably a passionate coach of
youth sports. Maybe your your kid, son,
daughter play soccer somewhere, and
you're like, "That's who I am. I like to
I like to use Team Snap." If you're OnX,
you're a hunter. Right? That's just who
you are. You're an outdoorsman, you're
rough, you're rugged. Like that's just
who you are. And so we've we kind of
took the pyramid, and we laid out
different CSS businesses that are
building for those different needs. And
the way we'd encourage founders to think
about that is is which And this is a
little esoteric, but it's like which
need are you targeting, right? If you're
going to do love and belonging, well,
man, you should have a community
function built into your app,
absolutely.
Right? If you're doing esteem, some sort
of leaderboard is a great way for people
to feel esteem by knowing where they are
in that leaderboard. Self-actualization,
you need to constantly putting new
content in so people can get better and
better at whatever they're trying to do.
Like, you know, if you're if it's a yoga
app, right? Or mental health, right?
There needs to be new content so they
get better and better at the yoga
practice. So, yeah, we think there's a
lot to think through here. It's it's a
new concept for us, a new framework
we're trying out, but we always like to
just think about not just stocks and
graphs, like looking backwards. We want
to look forwards, right? And see like
how do you How do you think about
building a new company or re-aiming an
existing company towards where the
market is or going to be. Yeah, the
graph is really fun, too. So, we'll
we'll provide a link to the full report
in the show notes. So, if if you haven't
already downloaded the report and
weren't following along, you should
definitely go check out this one graph
in particular. I mean, there's so much
great content, so they should definitely
download it either way, but I love the
way you you kind of sketch those out.
And like at the very top, you know, with
the self-actualization or things like
Reflectly, like an AI-powered journal
and Audible, you know, listening
audiobooks and learning and Calm, you
know, working on your your mental space.
Yeah, it's a fantastic chart and a great
exercise for folks to kind of plot
themselves on that chart. And if you
don't find a spot to plot yourself on
that chart, you
look look for the opening in the chart
where you should be aiming to fit on
that chart. So, I thought it was really
good. Another note that you put in there
that I just hadn't thought of and and I
feel like every report there's like one
or two lines that just kind of blow my
mind. And you said in there, "Consumer
spend accounts for 70% of the USD GDP."
And of course, a lot of that's going to
mortgage and car payments, like the base
needs of food, transportation, housing,
that those kind of things.
But when you think about and and as we
talked about last report, there's just a
lot of money being spent on a lot of
different areas. You know, OnX, which
you just mentioned, you know,
people are spending tens of thousands of
dollars a year as a hunter. These like
passions, these self-actualization, the
love and belonging, the community,
there's a lot of money going toward
these. And and consumer subscription
businesses building great products have
an opportunity to enter those markets
and capture
so much more of that spend than is
currently captured in the existing
products. And that that excites me about
kind of where we're headed headed as an
industry. Yeah, I think a lot of value
that used to be analog is being captured
digitally or those analog or physical
services are now being provided with
digital subscriptions attached to them.
And so, we think that's a really
exciting trend for us, right? You're
seeing this in healthcare, for sure.
You're starting to see it, you know,
like the Amazon buying One Medical,
right? That's a medical subscription
that now has a software tool driven
drive hopefully going to benefit health
care in the US, which is a heck of a
challenge, but So, these things that
previously were offline, you know,
health and safety, for example, the good
one, right? Like Life360, Citizen, these
are safety needs, right? That you
wouldn't normally think about being a
software subscription that people said
like, "Man, there's a gap there in the
market. I'm going to build something so
I know where my kids are." And then we
talk about like screen time, right?
That's kind of a safety issue, right?
Like who your kid who your kids
interacting with online.
Like that's those products should be
built and they're good, right? And so, I
think there's just more and more of the
world as it goes digital will just need
new solutions within that pyramid of
needs. So, yeah, we think it's a it's a
pretty wide opening area. And finding
places of value along this chart as
well. There's a company called Bright
Canary that I actually subscribe to and
it's one of the things like you just
wouldn't think this even necessarily
could exist, but I pay whatever it is,
six, eight, 10 bucks a month and don't
even think about it. Cuz what it does is
it actually tracks my kids YouTube
watching and then flags any concerning
content. And so, you know, as a parent,
I'm super concerned about what my kids
are exposed to online. So, it's like to
that screen time point, like as a
parent, paying eight bucks a month to
get a summary of what my kids are
watching on YouTube is like no-brainer,
no-brainer. And so, there's so many
opportunities like that to like find
things that people value and then build
products around it. And something like
Bright Canary, they're pretty unique in
the market and like that couldn't have
existed a few years ago and now it's
like a whole new segment that they can
go after of safety for kids online.
Yeah, we're seeing I mean there's some I
mean stuff like bird watching.
There's bird nests that have AR cameras
enabled. They'll tell you exactly what
showed up so you can learn like which
But what is a great business, man. Great
product. My mom I got my mom one this
year. Shout out that's also an adjacent
company, but There's another business I
love called Tractive that's in the dog
collar space. Dog collar, the most
non-technological thing ever. But now
they've added GPS and you're like, well,
that's cool. I live in a city, right? Do
I Does my dog I don't even know where my
dog is. It lives in a my apartment.
It's, you know, a tiny little pup. But
now they've added leaderboard functions,
right? So, you can see how much your pug
walked versus other pugs. And do you
want to be You want to be the parent
that doesn't walk their dog?
Right? So, all of a sudden now you're
starting to add more features in which
once you get all designed to keep your
dog healthy and safe, but like they've
added features that encourage you to go
do that and now was something that
probably doesn't need to exist three or
four years ago. It's freaking awesome. I
actually bought a Fi collar. Friend of
the podcast, Gerald Stone, is uh I think
uh VP of product there now. Fantastic
product. And then talking earlier about
NRR and market expansion, I just got an
ad in Fi. They're rolling out a head
supplement, like add this to your pet's
dog food to keep them healthy, make
their coat shinier and everything like
that. Super compelling offer. You once
you've got the attention with the value
prop of the GPS-enabled collar, which is
super fun, too. Like seeing how many
steps a dog has taken, seeing where they
land on the leaderboard. Like our whole
family is like super into it already.
And they have like massive market
expansion opportunity into the pet
market where we're spending, you know,
$200 a month on our dang dog.
Dave, it's not You're not spending $200
a month on your on your dang dog. You're
spending
$200 on a family member. True. Yes, of
course. Yeah, but that is probably your
cheapest family member. If we want to
start breaking out family members by
line items, David, it's probably one of
your cheaper, It is by far the cheapest
family member and I and I love him to
death. He's so sweet. But when I see the
bills come in and I'm a a bit of a tight
one.
They used to not cost that much. They
used to not cost that much. Lifestyle
creep, you know? Yeah, for sure. But
anyways, that was a great place to end.
I think there's You know, as saturated
as a market feels, like there's just so
much opportunity still. Opportunity for
existing businesses to grow and find new
layers of product market fit,
opportunities to expand their NRR,
opportunities to grow into other
markets. Like there there's so much
opportunity still in this space and and
even opportunity for brand new
businesses starting in 2024 to become
those IPO candidates in a few years. So,
really really fun place to be playing in
and really fun place to be working in
and really fun to talk to you about all
of this today. We love what we do every
day. We get to meet these awesome
businesses. So, yeah. Thanks for having
me again, guys. It's always a pleasure.
Yeah, awesome. So, we're going to link
to your LinkedIn and the the report and
the GP Bullhound website. Anything else
you want to share as we're wrapping up?
Nope. Like the best thing we love to
talk. Like just reach out. Like I'll be
at the Revenue Cat conference in San
Francisco on the 26th. So, if you're
there, say hi. But also just reach out.
Email me eric.crowley@gpbullhound.com.
Even if you're not looking to sell, like
that's okay. We don't need to talk to
you for that. We host CSS CEO dinners.
We love just getting operators together
to sit and talk and
decide where the opportunities are,
where we should build. So, You all need
to help Eric's deal flow is what he's
trying to say cuz like these pipelines
don't build themselves, baby. I think
we're we're going to we're doing pretty
well. I think we're pretty happy with
the reputation we have and and we get a
lot of a lot of great companies that
love to talk. I joke a little but like I
think it's You might not ever engage
with anybody for a transaction. It's
helpful to know people who can pin see
where you're at if you're ever thinking
about maybe doing it someday. And then
if you do ever want to work through a
transaction with somebody, it's helpful
to have known them for more than like
the life of the transaction.
No, we'll find out people all the time
if they just kind of call us out of the
blue. We like to know you for two or
three years. Like know what your goals
are, what your objectives like where the
weaknesses are, where the strengths.
Like spend time getting to know any
advisor regarding like lawyer,
accountant, like so they actually can
truly help you. Like don't just call
them up and say like, "Hey, you want to
do something?" Like this is an important
moment for your company. Like take the
time. All right. Well, it's so much fun
chatting, Eric, and I will see you in
San Francisco next week and see you on
the podcast again next year for the 2025
report.
Number six, seven, something like that.
I'd be honored to be considered.
Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.